[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right.
I hope you all
had a good break--
spring break, as they
call it, uncreatively.
I certainly had one.
Didn't do any work.
That's for sure.
Why would they put
this philosophy class
in an engineering building?
Hold on one moment, please.
I'm speaking, and I will get
to you when it's your turn.
I am Professor Breck Knowles.
This is Advanced Ethics.
You should be upper-class
philosophy majors.
That should be
all right in here.
Can you please wait your turn?
Please.
This is the textbook.
Now, this textbook covers some
of the most important topics
across ethics, edited, of
course, by yours truly.
[CHUCKLES]
I expect you all to have
it, and you can pull that--
none of you have it.
[SIGHS] The bookstore must have
really messed up this time.
No.
When you do get it, make sure
you get the new latest edition.
I don't get my cut
for used books.
Now, if you turn the page
432, that's my chapter.
Could you read?
[CLEARS THROAT]
Chapter 18, "Bias
is Bad," by Brack Know-less.
Knowles!
It's Knowles.
[SIGHS] You surely don't know
how to impress your professors.
You read.
When investigating the
societal implications of bias
within the framework of
non-hierarchical dependencies,
we must integrate that the
taxonomy of bias and inequity
are combinationally intertwined.
First and foremost, bias affects
both the sub- super-conscious--
Apologies for being late.
Computer systems
ask me to help fix
a glitch that
happened this morning
and affected which classrooms
a few professors are sent to.
Hi.
I'm Sophie Muller.
I don't think we've met.
That's what I was trying to tell
Professor Know-less, that he's
in the wrong classroom.
My apologies.
The problem with the software
upgrade this morning,
but it's all fixed.
This is not the advanced class?
No.
That's what I was
trying to tell you.
We are in engineering ethics.
Well, I always am supposed
to teach the advanced class.
I don't want to be
stuck with beginners.
But where am I supposed to go?
Let's see.
Knowles?
Your class is all of the way
back in the philosophy floor
in the subbasement of
building seven, room 001.
A bit of a hike, I'm afraid.
[CHUCKLES] Always get
stuck in the cave.
Excuse me.
Do you want your book back?
Thank you.
You engineers can make something
that US philosophers deserve.
Just--
[LAUGHTER]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
How is everyone doing?
Oh.
I guess I didn't introduce
myself to all of you.
I'm Sophie Muller.
I'll be taking over
from Professor Baer, who
has been asked to run
an important project
on the ethics of AI.
Did you have a
good spring break?
Yeah.
That's good, but the
registration list
said 40 students.
Where is everyone else?
Yeah.
Well, the others went to
go hear the president speak
about the new administrative
organizational structure.
He's changed it again.
Third time this year.
Mhm.
The university president.
Sounds interesting.
[CHUCKLING]
But I thought students almost
never go to such things.
Yes.
But since no one goes to
these and the president
didn't want to speak in front
of an empty auditorium again,
he offered everyone
free food and drink
and allowed them
to break the rules
and eat and drink
in the auditorium.
He also hired a large
steam cleaning crew,
complete with industrial
drying equipment
to clean up right afterwards.
I see.
Oh.
I realized that I
introduced myself
but got distracted
by our conversation
and didn't have you
introduce yourselves.
What are your names?
Alyssa.
I'm Patch.
My name is Sophie.
Alvis.
Glenda.
Pleased to meet you.
Well, nice to meet
all of you too.
So, you were telling me about
the event going on right now.
But why aren't you five there?
Yes, Sophie.
Well, professor, don't
tell anyone else,
but we're really
dedicated to understanding
the ethical issues
of bias in AI.
In fact, instead of
traveling over spring break,
we just stayed here to
discuss ethics altogether.
And we looked at the resources
that we could find online.
Your dedication is admirable.
What did you find
in your research?
Well, there are a bunch
of videos and articles
online, but--
But what?
We found them unsatisfying.
Why is that?
Alyssa.
Well, not everyone
found them unsatisfying.
I thought they made
some good points.
Well, you weren't able to
explain away their failings.
Were you?
No, but you weren't able
to give a better approach.
Were you?
Hold on, you two.
Always bickering.
We didn't answer
professor's question.
Professor Muller, we found
them unsatisfying because they
didn't give us an answer.
That's right.
They told us that
it's a problem,
and they said that
it's a hard problem,
but they didn't tell
us how to address it.
It's more than that.
The videos on bias in
AI are all the same.
They all say it's in
the data set-- bias in,
bias out-- and they keep
recycling the same examples.
Some videos have better
graphics or better speakers,
but other than that,
they're all the same.
[SCOFFS] So conformist.
Yeah.
And while they say that
bias is in the data set,
there seems to be
no general solution.
They just indicate that for
each algorithm the issue of bias
needs to be researched.
Even for that, they don't
give a systematic approach.
Yeah.
Even if you could choose
the right data set
and quantify it on
that data set to ensure
no bias in your training
set for a given analysis,
you have no way to know if
that applies to all situations.
My point is that we all
agree that bias is bad.
We simply need to address
it in every single algorithm
that we make.
Yes, I agree.
We don't want any
bias in our AI.
We want everyone to be happy.
This is a good start,
but perhaps it's
best if we get to specifics.
Alyssa, what were some of
the good points regarding
algorithmic bias
that you mentioned?
For example,
algorithms are biased
against underrepresented
minorities.
Facial recognition doesn't
work as well for Blacks
as it does for Whites,
especially Black women.
One common example shows
that while it identifies
White males nearly perfectly,
it misidentified Black woman
over 20% of the time.
Well, one algorithm gives
20% error and the other 30%.
They can't even be
consistent in their bias.
If we can't nail down the
extent of the problem,
how do we fix it?
You could at least work to
try to make sure that the data
set is more representative.
Oh, and what about the algorithm
that identifies Indian brides
as actors?
Well, why should they complain?
Being identified as an actor
is the greatest honor anyone
can have.
Oh, very funny.
I like chicken sandwiches.
How would you like it if
an algorithm identified you
as a chicken sandwich?
OK.
I see why they call it
an adversarial example.
In any case, it's not
easy to address bias
across the board
because of skews
in data sets due to
historical inequities.
And those skews differ.
At least we know that there
have been historical inequities
that we need to address.
And while it may
not be easy to do,
we have to at least try, even
if it's on a case-by-case basis.
Even if it is on a
case-by-case basis,
we're doomed to
miss a lot of bias
until long after
everyone is equal.
And I for one am
not that patient.
Well, this problem
is so important
that even if it takes a very
long time and even if we
have to do it
algorithm by algorithm,
that is what we should do.
If we all do this,
everyone will be happy.
But no, many people
won't be happy
waiting for the bias to go away.
So, professor, this is where
we got stuck over spring break.
It's just not
practical to engineer
every algorithm against bias.
Even if we could, we would
end up eliminating it
in a few dimensions.
But then we're bound to miss it
in other important dimensions.
Above and beyond
that, we can't even
quantify the bias consistently
since different studies
on the same data set give
different amounts of bias.
We know that we need to do
something to address bias,
but what the videos say will at
best take a small step forward.
We know that others may
be content with that,
but it's not sufficient for us
to feel good about ourselves.
No, it's not.
Ah.
You have reached an impasse,
which, believe it or not,
is often a necessary place to
be before you can make progress.
I think, however, it's best if
we take a step back and explore
how these algorithms work
and the roots of wanting
to eliminate bias.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So you probably all know
this, but just to remind you,
the overall approach is simple.
You start out with a
training set of data
here together with descriptors,
which we use to derive a model.
Then we input the data,
and the model classifies it
based on some criterion.
Obviously, the devil
is in the details.
Based on this
high-level approach,
where do you see bias?
There's no bias here.
The algorithm-- say, a
convolutional neural network--
objectively analyzes
the data provided to it.
It's just math.
It is not just math.
We choose the training set.
We choose the algorithm.
Even if we think that
we are not biased,
we are subconsciously biased.
How do we actually
choose them if everything
is described by mathematics?
We don't really have a choice.
Duh.
The bias is already in the data
due to historical inequity.
You said it yourself.
So then our choice is
to note that and add
an appropriate loss function.
Does everybody know
what a loss function is?
Of course.
Yes.
Yeah.
A loss function is
just the error function
associated with an event,
such as facial recognition.
It is what should be
mathematically minimized.
Good.
Just to clarify, it
shouldn't be simply minimized
across the board but
targeted, for example,
so that the overall error
in facial recognition
is minimized with the
constraint that it is
equal among different groups.
But unless you have
equivalent training sets
for the different groups,
the statistical errors
won't be equivalent.
And you can't quantify
the errors in advance
to determine whether or not
they will be equivalent.
In other words, you can't choose
the loss function approach
to solve the problem because
the fluctuations or randomness.
The problem is statistics.
We have to have
a very large data
set to average out randomness
to acceptably small percentages
and make sure that our
data is representative.
Yes, but my point is that
it's just not possible.
I agree that we
could make the error
rates in facial
recognition algorithms
equal for Whites and Blacks
and for men and women.
But what about all the other
racial and ethnic minorities?
And for that matter, what about
all the different genders?
Even if we could
agree on what groups
need to have bias eliminated,
we can't practically
address them all.
Yeah, and that's not
even how the field works.
No one's going to spend five
or 10 years for each algorithm
to eliminate bias.
For cutting-edge
research, people just
try to hit 80%, sometimes 90%
accuracy for a given algorithm
and then publish a paper on it.
The incentives are such
that they can't spend years
getting 99% or so accuracy
across the board, at least
for new algorithms.
There just isn't enough data.
Better to just get
something out there,
even if it's not so good, so
you at least get credit for it.
If we could only
eliminate randomness,
our problems would be solved.
But randomness is good because
it's the basis of choice,
otherwise our minds would just
follow a deterministic path
based on our neural pathways
and electrical signals.
The heart of it is
quantum mechanics,
which introduces
intrinsic randomness.
Well, randomness doesn't
give you choice, just chaos.
That's also the
reason we have bias
to begin with, because of
random historical circumstances.
We want to eliminate bias,
not just make it random.
If it is random, then
maybe you will mitigate it
for minorities, or
maybe, at least for some,
you'll find a way to augment it.
[SCOFFS] That is what
I was saying, too.
So we seem to be stuck again.
Mathematics is the rigorous
way to understand the world,
but it doesn't give us choice.
In the world described
by mathematics,
choice is an illusion.
Professor, we ran
into the same impasse
when we had this discussion
last week during spring break.
But how do we get out of it?
I think I can be
of some help here.
So you all agree that it is
desirable to eliminate bias,
right?
Yeah.
Yes.
So you all think it is possible
to mitigate bias depending
on what actions you take?
Yeah.
So you do think that can make
choices and not just randomly.
More well-grounded
choices are better than
less well-grounded ones,
say, for addressing bias.
I don't think we really
have a choice about things.
People might think that they
do, but they don't really.
We can't choose where we are
born or how smart we are,
and we can't choose if
we get hit by a car.
We think we are making a
choice, but we really aren't.
It's like Sophie said.
It's all just an illusion.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're right.
Randomness doesn't help.
You've convinced me.
Wait.
Did I have a choice, or
was I compelled to agree?
No.
Your neurons told you to agree.
Yes, exactly.
And randomness, a consequence
of a chaotic quantum process,
just makes what we
do not predictable
but doesn't mean that
we choose what we do.
Right.
Well, you have a choice whether
you're going to be biased
or not.
Mhm.
Indeed.
It does seem that
judgments involve choice.
But Alyssa, if you were
given the full understanding
of a situation, wouldn't you
always take the best action?
Yeah, of course.
No.
You can't really choose whether
anything is better or worse.
It's all just a value judgment.
You may be compelled to
do something by others,
but you never really
freely choose.
Do you really believe
that, or are you
just playing devil's advocate?
OK.
A little of both.
But even if I am just
playing devil's advocate,
what's wrong with
what I'm saying?
What's wrong is that your model
of human life is inadequate.
It doesn't describe
what it really is.
We're not just some balls
moving around deterministically
with random noise interspersed
like a term in a Langevin
equation.
Isn't that true,
Professor Muller?
What a great discussion this is.
Sounds like you had
a much better spring
break discussing these questions
than going to the beach.
[CHUCKLES]
I think you're on the
right track, Sophie.
Funny.
Coincidentally, that's
my first name too.
At any rate, you have
unveiled a great tension
in modern science.
We are brought up to think
that modern science is the way
to describe the
world, but it seems
inadequate to
describe human things.
Ethical questions cannot be
reducible to mathematics--
similar to justice and
beauty, hope and suffering,
and, for that
matter, even truth.
Yes, Glenda.
Aren't those things even more
important than modern science?
I would say so.
No.
Those things are
arbitrary or a matter
of individual's interests--
what's in it for them.
That's the way to look
at them scientifically.
Bias exists because people
have conflicting interests.
Sure, if you look at it
purely scientifically,
but interest alone cannot
be adequate since people are
willing to sacrifice interests
for passions and, more
importantly, for things
beyond themselves.
At any rate, do most
of us really know
all of our interests?
We all have preferences that
go far beyond interests.
Perhaps we can say at best that
those interests are intertwined
with different
approaches to the world.
Besides, aren't the most
boring people the ones who say,
I'm right, and, even if one
can never make value judgments,
I have my own values
and I stick with them?
[CHUCKLES] Yeah, these are
the most irritating and boring
people.
So, now let's dig down a bit
more into the mathematics
of AI and the sorting problem.
Perhaps it's best to start
with a specific example.
What's the reason for the
bias in facial recognition
that we discussed
a little while ago?
A biased training set due
to historical inequity.
OK.
So one of the issues
is the training set.
The other issue
is the algorithm,
including its hyperparameters,
all leading to how
the classification is done.
This is why different algorithms
give different error rates
using the same training data.
Anything else?
Right.
So those are the two key issues.
However, within the
choice of algorithm,
there is the problem
with classification.
Let me project
this data set, here
with points in red and blue.
You have many choices for
putting the dividing surface.
But what if we
choose the wrong one?
Some of the data may be
misclassified, won't it?
You mean like this?
Yes, exactly.
So how do you choose the
right line ahead of time?
That is a problem.
It could be even worse if
your data set looks like this.
But then we don't have
to stick with lines.
Why don't you draw
a curve around them?
Like this?
Yes, exactly.
Now you've classified
them all perfectly.
Well, wait a second.
If you do that, it works
for the training set,
but it may not work for
any additional data sets.
In fact, it might be
even worse than the lines
because you're overfitting
to the training data.
Do you mean like this?
Yeah.
That doesn't work.
Oh, yes.
I see it.
Exactly.
Remember this is a sorting
algorithm, here in two
dimensions with two descriptors,
thus it is quite limited.
But even if you do it in a very
large number of dimensions with
a very large number
of descriptors,
you are still projecting
a complicated system--
shall we say a natural system--
onto an artificial
mathematical construct
that necessarily leaves
much out of the description.
Or if you want to stay in
the realm of mathematics,
you could say that due to
a necessary incomplete set
of descriptors you
were fitting noise.
This allows you to get a perfect
fit for your training set,
but then you have an even
worse fit for your data set
moving forward.
Patch.
In other words, we
have to accept the fact
that there will be errors.
But at least we could distribute
the errors evenly among groups.
That is what Alyssa said before.
We can try, but
then I'm worried we
won't include all the groups.
Even if we could, there'll
be errors in the errors.
Unless we have a very,
very large training
set, which practically
we never have,
we won't be able to do that.
Yes.
The training set would
have to incorporate
all the data in the world.
You know, that
reminds me of a story
I once heard, I think from
a South American writer,
where someone makes a one-to-one
scale map of their country
with all the details included.
[CHUCKLES]
Ha, ha.
Well, I grant the problem.
But then what do we do?
We all agree that we
need to eliminate bias,
but it seems so hard.
What if we could at least
have a very extensive model
that for all practical purposes
captures a given situation?
Which I guess is
actually impossible
because it would require a
complete and accurate model
of all the objects
in the whole world.
Yes.
As engineers, we can at
least work to do that.
If the model is extensive
enough, we can eliminate bias.
But then we'd be eliminating any
choice that we might have had.
We would be controlled
by an algorithm.
That sounds-- that
sounds tyrannical.
Indeed.
Mathematization of human
things distorts them so much
that they become something
which they are not.
This is actually the
utilitarian approach.
Human things like joy, anger,
justice, honor, beauty,
and happiness are really
not mathematizable.
We lose all of what
is important in them
when we mathematize them.
We could in principle try to
do so and therein transform
human reality.
Glenda.
That doesn't sound appealing.
It sounds dreadful.
Yeah, that wouldn't be good.
But we can at least do
it partially, can't we?
Yes.
Maybe that would
be a good solution.
Yes.
Even if those human
things cannot be described
by mathematics, it is still the
only rigorous way to understand
the world.
I'm not so sure anymore, but
the bias is in the data set,
and it is in the algorithms.
So we must be able to adjust
our models to solve the problem.
Mustn't we?
Well, consider this-- our
recognition of the problem
of bias is not mathematical.
Mathematics comes only
after such recognition.
Mathematics is something
we impose on our broader
understanding of the world.
We can use it to develop
models, but they will always
be just that, models
which are necessarily
incomplete descriptions.
I see what you're
saying, I think.
Sophie.
But AI is based on mathematics.
So we have to fix this
problem in the algorithms
via fixing the algorithms, i.e.
by using mathematics.
Don't we?
Well, we can think
of things this way,
but that will lead us
to a double whammy.
We cannot develop a
non-arbitrary definition
of the criteria for the
training set, and, two,
we cannot develop a
non-arbitrary definition
of the error target for
the sorting algorithm.
Well, I knew that we
were at an impasse,
but I didn't think it
was this big of one.
Professor, your
class has made us
more stuck than we were before.
So, what do we do?
Is there another way?
Indeed, Glenda, there is that.
It requires a reconsideration of
our concerns and of the issue.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[DOOR CLOSES]
Thank you.
Sophie.
So, what is the other way?
Well, let's think about it.
We just showed that because of
the intrinsic incompleteness
of models eliminating
bias in all dimensions
is mathematically impossible.
We could no doubt decrease
bias among some groups
to a certain degree, with an
acceptably small but still
significant margin of error.
Even if we got rid of bias in
some predefined dimensions,
we would still have it
in other dimensions.
But that's precisely it.
We want equality in at
least some dimensions,
the important ones.
That is good.
How do you choose which
dimensions are important?
Alvis.
One important
dimension is wealth.
Good.
So even you five, the
top engineering students
in your class at the top
engineering school, should get
paid just as much as someone
like Dean, the paper collector.
Well, he is a very nice
fellow, if a bit strange.
But no, we think we should be
rewarded for the contributions
that we make to society.
But wealth should be
distributed more equally.
That's right.
But how do you decide
how equal it should be?
Perhaps the problem
is once again
that mathematics in its
homogenization of kinds
is not the right way
to address the problem.
Let me ask you this--
is it really equality that
you want, or is it justice?
Justice.
Yeah.
I'll go with justice.
Great that you two
agree on something.
Glenda.
They should go hand in
hand, justice and equality.
Yeah.
Isn't equality justice?
I think we need to add
another consideration,
since we are beginning to
delve into the complex human
questions underlying
our definition
and perception of bias.
So let me ask you this.
Which is most important--
equality, justice,
or happiness?
Sophie.
I would say happiness.
Even if someone has
more than you do,
and even if they
don't deserve it,
it doesn't matter to you
as long as you are happy.
Think of all the people
born into rich families.
They're typically
not happy since they
don't need to have a goal, and
therefore they don't have one.
I would still have a goal if I
were born into a rich family.
Why do they need
a goal if they're
having such a good time?
Because people need to
have a purpose to be happy.
And how can people be happy
if they're not treated fairly?
So we have equality,
justice, and happiness,
but it is unclear which
is most important.
Glenda.
Can't they be of
equal importance?
Actually, no.
They are certainly interrelated.
But since they are at
least somewhat different
and since, as we saw, they
can conflict, one of them
has to be most important, has to
take precedence over the other.
I think that justice is more
important than equality.
After all, we don't want
everyone to be the exact same,
but still justice and
equality are related.
People can be unequal because
they're treated unfairly.
They can also be unequal
due to luck, good or bad.
I don't think that happiness
can be the standard.
We need equality, and that's
why mathematics is still
so important, because we
can employ it rigorously
to make everyone equal.
But if everyone is the same,
wouldn't the world be drab?
I mean, what if all
of us were the same?
We wouldn't even be able to
have this dialogue, as we'd all
be making the same point.
There would be
nothing interesting,
as everyone is reduced
to a forced homogeneity.
Besides, how do
you make everyone
equal without
violating their rights?
We're going to have to
violate some rights to make
people at least more equal.
But then maybe I guess
that's not justice.
Yeah.
Isn't it the essence of tyranny
when rights are violated
in the name of justice?
Yes.
We have strong reasons
not to want that.
We want equality,
but we certainly
don't want to violate
people's rights to get it.
But what do we do?
Here we are at an impasse again.
How do we understand
this conflict
between equality and rights?
By the way, professor,
what about that other way
that you promised?
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I was wondering when you
would want to go to that.
Do you remember learning
about modern natural right
from Professor Baer
before spring break?
Yes, a bit.
We studied Locke's state of
nature and its connection
with natural right, if that's
what you're talking about.
Professor Baer
also made the case
that modern natural right is the
basis for the American regime
and the reason for
this country's success.
Good.
And yes, that is
exactly what I mean.
It's great that you
remember reading
Locke and about
modern natural right
being the basis for
the American regime.
Oh.
Hello, Professor Knowles.
What are you doing here?
I hope I'm not bothering you.
I heard that you were
discussing modern natural right,
and I wanted to join.
The stuff you heard
me spew earlier
was a front that I
have to put forward
to my colleagues in the
philosophy department,
and some students who
appreciate such things.
It's the only way I
could keep a job, which
I need to be able to
pursue true philosophy.
That is refreshing to hear.
And yes, please do join us.
We were just starting
on modern natural right.
So how does Locke view the
problem of AI and bias?
Patch.
Locke would think it
wrong because bias
violates your natural right.
Yes, I agree.
That sounds right,
but I'm not sure
because we said that justice is
more important than equality.
But it seems that equality
is fundamental in Locke.
But then where is
justice in Locke?
Let's take this step by step.
Does anyone remember
the beginning?
But you said you were
working on these questions
during spring break.
Alvis?
Well, we were discussing them,
but we never actually went back
to the texts from class.
Yeah.
We just wanted to figure
them out for ourselves.
I guess you disapprove,
Professor Muller?
On the contrary.
You are a very
impressive group to have
stayed here over spring
break and investigated
these questions.
Any teacher would be thrilled to
have even one student like you,
and I have five.
But you said that you got stuck.
What was your plan to
get out of your impasse?
Well, your class, of course.
[LAUGHS]
Hush, Patch.
You seem not to realize
that Professor Muller is
in a most mild way
rebuking us for not
using the resources at hand.
Well, let's use them now.
Professor, please remind us
of Locke's starting point.
Of course.
Let's turn to second
treatise, chapter 1.
Professor Knowles, where do
you think we should start?
I'd say the last section
of paragraph one,
starting with "he that."
That is exactly
what I was thinking.
Glenda, could you
read the statement
starting with "he that?"
Of course.
He that will not
give just occasion
to think that all
government in the world
is the product of only
force and violence
must of necessity find out
another rise of government.
Good.
So Locke is giving
us two options
of the origin of government,
force or something else--
maybe something
else based on reason
but not narrow or
mathematical reason.
Yes, of course.
That is much better.
It would be terrible to
think that politics is just
about force.
I agree.
It should be about
allowing people
to be happy, as we said before.
But what does this
alternative basis?
You can look at your
books, you know.
Alvis.
It is the state of nature.
Good.
What is the state of nature?
Well, let's see.
I actually underlined
this pretty extensively.
It is a state of perfect freedom
and a state also of equality.
Yes.
I remember now.
But how can it be a
state of perfect freedom
if anyone can take your
stuff and it's only up to you
to protect it?
You don't remember?
That's the point.
There is no government,
so we're all
perfectly free in that sense.
But life is not
desirable since we're
all individually vulnerable.
That's why we form
governments, for security.
Very good, Sophie, but
you're moving too fast.
Remember Locke says but though
this be a state of liberty,
yet it is not a
state of license.
Do you recall why that is?
Oh, hold on.
I have it right here.
Because of a law of nature.
Yes, that's it.
Laws of nature are
based on reason.
Yeah.
We talked about that
before spring break.
Now I remember.
It's dumb to waste stuff,
including your own life.
What about these people
that waste their money
on luxuries, expensive
cars and things?
Yeah.
I'd be content with
a cheap rundown car.
Why should someone buy a
Ferrari when most of us
can't afford an old Kia?
Does anyone recall
Locke's answer to this?
Perhaps, once again,
we are moving too fast.
Let's go step by step.
What is the state
of nature like?
Alvis.
In addition to freedom and
equality, there is a law.
Good.
What else?
There is punishment.
In paragraph seven, he
says everyone has a right
to punish the transgressors
of that law to such a degree
as may hinder its violation.
Very good, Sophie.
I think we will see that
our objection to bias
is itself based on a sense
that there is a law of nature.
How does Locke characterize
this statement?
He says in paragraph nine that
this will seem a very strange
doctrine to some.
Excellent.
Does it seem strange to you?
Well, not any more strange
than the state of nature.
Why is the state
of nature strange?
So nature is what you
experience when you go on a hike
or go camping.
What Locke is describing
never really existed.
What do you think
existed in its place?
So humans evolved
from humanoids,
and they lived in tribes.
They weren't by themselves.
Right, Patch.
But what is the basis of the
rule of the tribe leader?
Power.
But isn't this exactly what
Locke said at the beginning?
We can have tribal
rule based on power,
or we can have an alternative,
which Locke provides.
Besides, don't you think
human beings' natural state is
freedom and equality?
That all makes sense.
But then why does Locke call
it a very strange doctrine?
To some.
See, I think that will
find that what is required
is not so much a new doctrine,
say a learned latent structure
for algorithmic bias mitigation
or domain adaptation,
but a reflection
on what doctrine
some find strange
and others do not.
What's strange to us actually
contradicts our own biases.
Psychologically, we tend
to resist those things
because they point out
our biases to ourselves.
Oh, I see.
What we find strange is an
indication of our own bias.
That's what Locke is saying.
Thank you, Professor Knowles.
And I realize that he
defends this doctrine
by arguing that governments
can punish foreigners
who break a law,
which is related
to the example in
paragraph 14, when he says
that by the state of nature
exists today, since all princes
and rulers of
independent governments
all through the world
are in a state of nature.
Very good, and then he
brings in the next paragraph
the weight of the writings
of Hooker, or shall
we say the judicious Hooker.
And he ends the chapter
with the idea of consent.
So political society is made
legitimate only by consent.
Well, since we
are short on time,
I'll have to move on to
chapter five on property.
But explore when
you can what he says
about the state of war and
slavery in the Skip chapters.
We will also come back
to other subtleties,
like why he calls the
doctrine by everyone
in the state of nature
has executive power
this strange doctrine
in paragraph 13
and, for that
matter, why there is
no authority in the state of
nature besides each individual.
So what are his key
arguments on property?
Alyssa.
One is that each of us has a
property in our own person.
That's in paragraph 27.
Good.
And later in paragraph 27, that
we make things our property
by mixing our labor
with things from nature.
Very good.
Yeah.
I like the acorn example.
By picking up an
acorn, we make it ours.
I guess that applies
to fruit, too.
[LAUGHTER]
And he says in paragraph
26 that the Earth is ours
for the support and
comfort of our being
and that we're given
reason to use it well.
That brings me back to
my point from before.
Someone isn't using it
well if they're rich
and they hoard things.
Well, you can only
hoard so much.
Like, who needs 10 Ferraris?
I do.
Ha, ha.
Ha, ha, yourself.
The point is that you cannot
hoard because your things will
spoil.
Yes.
That is why he talks
about money somewhere.
Money doesn't go bad.
Yes, in paragraph 36.
But you'll see that he
says in paragraph 31
that everyone can take as
much as he wants from nature,
but there is a limitation.
What is that limitation that
prevents us from accumulating
so much that things spoil?
Well, what is also present
in nature besides things
you can take?
Oh, yes.
The law of reason.
It's stupid to hoard because
then you're just wasting stuff,
and that's against
the law of reason.
But once there is money, you
can hoard it without spoiling.
So why isn't that wrong to do?
Because you put
your labor into it?
But what if you're just lucky?
Or what if you inherited it?
OK if I answer this one?
It's because someone else
put their labor into it,
therefore they can give
however they choose.
Excellent.
Thanks.
Do you recall how much
Locke says labor increases
the value of what is in nature?
100 times in paragraph 40.
1,000 times in paragraph 43.
Both 10 and 100 times
in paragraph 37.
And since we mentioned
paragraph 40,
we should point out
his famous statement
in the subsequent one.
A king of a large and
fruitful territory in America
feeds, lodges, and is clad worse
than a day laborer in England.
So whatever the
factor of increase is,
the point is not just that
labor is almost all the value
in property but that
by protecting property
we will all benefit
with many good things.
Yes, like this university.
[CHUCKLES]
Exactly.
I still don't think it's fair
that some people have so much
more than others.
But we all benefit.
Besides, if it weren't
for this system,
you wouldn't even be able
to get that broken-down Kia
that you dream of.
Oh.
Ha, ha.
[LAUGHTER]
But even if the pie
gets bigger and bigger,
some people will
still control others
because they have
a bigger piece,
making those people unhappy.
Or do you mean less free?
If so, it seems that AI doesn't
solve the problem at all.
Of course, some people
do think that it can,
that mathematization
of all things
can lead to a sort
of techno utopia.
Locke is giving us a choice.
We can be controlled by
algorithms designed by smart
but unworldly people working
long hours in some basement--
or let's call it a cave--
or we can be allowed
our own choice.
Of course, that choice
should be the product
of thoughtful reflection,
particularly on our own biases.
But AI could give more
freedom, couldn't it?
I see what you're saying.
Certainly, it can bring
benefits in health care
and transportation and make
many things more efficient.
But intrinsically it
can't solve the problem
of bias even in itself.
Actually, it's even worse.
Those who develop and
therefore control AI
will build AI systems biased
for their own benefit.
Hmm.
Having said that, I
realized that we somehow
seem to have gotten
distracted from understanding
how natural right can help
us to address bias in AI.
And we only have a few
minutes of class left.
I was wondering when you
were going to realize that.
Well, you convinced
us that all AI systems
will be biased in
some dimensions
no matter what you do.
But then you also
convinced us that property
should be respected.
So, what do we do about bias?
Yeah.
And how should we
punish people who write
unacceptably biased AI systems?
Or reward them for making
acceptably biased AI systems.
I mean unbiased AI systems.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
We can't reward
or punish people,
according to Locke's system.
On the contrary,
we can reward them
by buying their
products if we like them
or punish them by not
buying their products
if we don't like them.
So transparency is the key?
Yes, if people are willing
to pay for transparency.
You see, the law of
nature addresses that too.
And in most
contemporary approaches,
there is an
assumption, one which
we have been
addressing today too,
that bias is bad and
should be eradicated
by technical mathematical means.
We now understand that a deeper
reflection on the law of nature
and the law of reason is
needed, but we engineers
needed to see the limitations
of the mathematical or computer
science approach
first before we turn
to a broader or deeper one.
Yeah.
I think I understand
this now, but it still
hasn't changed one thing.
I want a Ferrari.
[SCOFFING, CHUCKLING]
The point is under the Lockean
system we are all better off--
happier, we could say--
because algorithms
with unacceptable
bias will go away because
no one will buy them.
You're starting to understand.
Earlier, you mentioned
utilitarianism,
and you showed not only
that AI is tied up in it
but that it doesn't treat
the human things well.
But what I didn't
really understand
is that we still need to
make utilitarian choices,
like allocation of resources.
Could you show us how to
think about that necessity
within the realm
of human things?
Yes, I can.
We did say that utilitarianism
as a form of thought
tends to give an incomplete
account of human concerns
and passions, no
matter how much we
strive to make the
mathematical model complete.
But we did indicate that
engineering is utilitarian
and that it always strives
to optimize some function.
How we should think about
that for human benefit
would be the subject
for next class.
[BELL RINGS]
[MUSIC PLAYING]